Guide to the World's Columbian Exposition ticket collection, 1893 MS2274
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
World's Columbian Exposition ticket collection
circa 1864-circa 1875
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2274
0.25 Linear Feet 1 slim document box
This collection contains ten tickets from the World's Columbian Exposition Chicago 1893. There are also two pieces of United States fractional currency and an envelope from the Caxton Co. that may have held the tickets. The fractional currency is dated circa 1864-circa 1875 while all the tickets are for the year 1893.
Arrangement
This collection is not organized in any particular order.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquisition information for this collection is unknown.
Historical note
The World's Columbian Exposition (also called The Chicago World's Fair), was held in Chicago in 1893. The fair celebrated the 400th anniversary of Christopher Columbus's arrival in the New World. Chicago bested New York City, Washington, D.C. and St. Louis, Missouri, for the honor of hosting the fair. The fair had a profound effect on architecture, the arts, Chicago's self-image, and American industrial optimism. Daniel Burnham and Frederick Law Olmsted had the most influence designing the Exposition. Burhman and Olmstead followed Beaux Arts principles of design, namely, European Classical Architecture principles based on symmetry and balance.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains ten tickets from the World's Columbian Exposition Chicago. Most of the tickets admit the bearer for the entire time of the fair May 1, 1893 through October 30, 1893, though there is a date of sale ticket, a Chicago Day only ticket, and a Manhattan Day only ticket. The collection also contains two pieces of United States fractional currency. One is for $.25 and the other for $.10. The final item in this collection is an envelope from the Caxton Co. This envelope may have held these tickets. The tickets are all date 1893. The currency has been dated based on the span of dates for the issue number of that particular currency and falls between 1864 and 1875.
Paper money -- United States; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket (George Washington portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago complimentary ticket (Benjamin Franklin portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago Music ticket (George Frideric Handel portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket (Native American portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket (Abraham Lincoln portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket (Roman profile portrait), 1893 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago Children's Special Ticket, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket Expressly for Manhattan Day, 10/21/1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket Expressly for Chicago Day, 10/09/1893 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- World's Columbian Exposition Chicago ticket Good Only on Day of Sale, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- United States Fractional Currency $.25 cents, circa. 12/1864 - circa. 08/1869 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Scope and Contents
  Part of the 3rd issue. This is paper money with the image of Secretary of the Treasury (1864) Fessenden. It is pasted to a board and only the portrait side is visible.
- United States Fractional Currency $.10 cents, circa. 07/1869 -circa. 02/1875 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Part of the 4th issue. This is paper money with image of Miss Liberty. It is pasted to a board and only the portrait side is visible.
- Envelope from the Caxton Co., undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Outside of envelope reads "All remaining World's Fair Souvenir Tickets have been sold, and THE CAXTON COMPANY controls the same. This envelope contains a set of these tickets. THE CAXTON CO., 334 Dearborn Street, CHICAGO